<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Authority abused by the vindication of the last years transactions, and the abuses detected with inlargements upon some particulars more briefly touched in the Reflectons upon the occurrences of the last year : together with some notes upon another vindication, entituled, The third and last part of the magistry ans government of England vindicated / by the author of the Reflections.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11926307</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11926307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Authority abused by the vindication of the last years transactions, and the abuses detected with inlargements upon some particulars more briefly touched in the Reflectons upon the occurrences of the last year : together with some notes upon another vindication, entituled, The third and last part of the magistry ans government of England vindicated / by the author of the Reflections.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed in the Year,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus).  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reflections upon the occurrences of the last year attributed to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus). Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shower, Bartholomew, --  Sir, 1658-1701. --  Third and last part of the magistry and government of England vindicated.</term>
               <term>Last years transactions, vindicated.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AUTHORITY ABUSED BY The VINDICATION Of the Laſt Years <hi>Tranſactions,</hi> AND The ABUSES DETECTED; WITH INLARGEMENTS upon ſome Particulars more briefly touched in the <hi rend="blackletterType">Reflections upon the Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of the Laſt Year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH Some NOTES upon another Vindication, Entituled, <hi>The Third and Laſt Part of the Magiſtracy and Government of</hi> England <hi>Vindicated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Author of the REFLECTIONS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Magna eſt</hi> VERITAS, <hi>&amp; Praevalebit.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51025:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN I firſt came in to you to <hi>Sherborn,</hi> I came with as much Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, though in an infirm Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to engage in the ſame Cauſe with you, as I could have done to a good Meal when an hungred. And though you are now ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Throne, and the Storms of War which then threatned this Nation, long ſince blown over: Yet I have reaſon to believe I may run ſome Danger in what I now do for the Service of your Majeſty and my Country. And though I doubt not of the Protection of Almighty God, and the powerful Supports of Truth, Juſtice, and a good Conſcience; yet becauſe it is my Duty to neglect no honeſt Means for my Safety and Quiet, having here performed an Act of Great Fidelity to your Majeſty, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of my Country, I do claim as my Right
<pb facs="tcp:51025:3"/>the Protection of both for my ſelf, and my Labours. I have not written one Syllable which I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be true; nor have I forborn a Word, which I thought pertinent to my Subject, and neceſſary to your Service. And this being done, not out of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content for any Diſappointment <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthily ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, not without the Check of his own Conſcience,</hi> by the Writer of the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. <hi>p.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>in queſt of ſome Place,</hi> (for I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſought any, though I my ſelf, with Five Sons, are all ready to ſerve you, if you pleaſe to command it) nor to ſerve any Faction or Party; but ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to preſerve one of the Nobleſt Governments in the World, (as I have long thought it) to ſerve a Juſt and Noble Cauſe, (as I have elſe where, though briefly, proved) to ſerve my Country, to ſerve your Majeſty, and, which is above all, to ſerve Almighty God, is ſuch an Act of Fidelity, as is too rare to be met with in this Nation at this time: And I know you cannot deſert me in it, without deſerting (more or leſs) all that I have endeavoured to ſerve: Nor can any one hurt or moleſt me (an innocent Man, and endeavouring to do good) without bringing greater hurt upon themſelves: Whereof he who gave occaſion of this Writing may be an Example:) And beſides, without ſtriking at your Majeſty and the Government, to ſay no more.</p>
            <p>For the ſame intent and purpoſe, beſides what I have ſaid in <hi>the following Sheets in common,</hi> I muſt
<pb facs="tcp:51025:3"/>crave the Favour of <hi>a few Words to your ſelf</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: God by his Providence has brought you to one (as I ſaid) of the Nobleſt Governments in the World: That You and theſe Nations may enjoy the Compleat Benefit of ſo great a Favour, theſe things, I will preſume to ſay, are neceſſary, nay abſolutely neceſſary, on your part. Firſt, That you be very careful to keep up ſuch a firm and quick Senſe of the Providence of God in theſe things, that your Heart be neither ſo lifted up with any high Conceit of your ſelf for what you have already gotten, nor ſo involved in Cares and Endeavours to keep that, or get more, that you forget him, and either take up with the Enjoyment of theſe things, and neglect the further Proſecution of his Service; or deſerting your Confidence in him, decline to vulgar Policies for your own Security or Advantage.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That often contemplating the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable Excellence of the Divine Majeſty, which hath given Being to, and governs this vaſt Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, whereof the whole Earth is in compariſon of the reſt but a Point, and raiſing <hi>your Soul</hi> above theſe tranſient things which the Vulgar admire, you look upon the <hi>Acceptance of a Crown</hi> as an <hi>Act of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to poor Mortals, but your <hi>only true Glory</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the Approbation of that excellent Majeſty, and of his Glorious, though to us Mortals Inviſible, Miniſters. Such as is the Applauſe and Admiration
<pb facs="tcp:51025:4"/>of the Rabble to a great King; ſuch, and no more, is the Applauſe and Admiration of the greateſt of Mortals to a truly Wiſe Man, without the Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Celeſtial Spectators.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That aſſuring your ſelf that you are <hi>rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by the Providence of this Glorious Majeſty for his Service</hi> in theſe Nations at leaſt, if not further, you generouſly proſecute the ſame with all Fidelity, according to his Will and Pleaſure, that is, his Eternal Laws of Righteouſneſs, his Expreſs Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Commands, and the Conſtitution and juſt Laws of this Government and Nation, which is the ſpecial Ordinance of God for this People, that is, ordered and preſerved by his Providence.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That for that purpoſe you generouſly and faithfully endeavour to <hi>improve all the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages</hi> put into your Hand, and Talents committed to your Truſt, for the Honour of his Name, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Laws and Inſtitutions; that is, the Exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Authority of your Royal Perſon, and of your Royal Family, (conniving at no vitious Perſons there, though otherwiſe never ſo great or neceſſary) the Diſpenſations of your Honours and Favours, and the ſtrict Execution of the Laws, which is your proper part in the Government. The doing of this magnanimouſly, ſlighting the vulgar Prudentials of Animal Polititians, is that which in the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is called Faith, and highly recommended. But to
<pb facs="tcp:51025:4"/>boggle at any of this, will be dangerous to you, and may produce as great Diſappointments as thoſe of the laſt Year, and make your Counſels prove Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and it may be as deſtructive as King <hi>James</hi>'s did by the like means. You have begun well in your Letter to the Biſhops; but the like Care is to be taken that the Laws be ſtrictly executed by the Judges and Civil Magiſtrates. Nor would this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe, but Improve your Military Diſcipline, and make it more proſperous and ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That to this end and purpoſe alſo you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your ſelf, as well as may be, concerning <hi>the true Conſtitution of the Engliſh Government,</hi> and your own Part therein, that you neither neglect, nor exceed your Duty, or fall into any of the unhappy Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of ſome of your Predeceſſors, but wiſely and religiouſly contenting your ſelf with what has been conferred upon you, and juſtly belongs to you, to the others you generouſly ſecure to each their own.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, That for Information in theſe matters you rely upon no private or ſecret Counſellors, but in the Intervals of Parliament, conſult the Privy Council and Judges; and the great Council of the Nation, as ſoon as may be: This it was which raiſed you to the Throne. It is their Intereſt to preſerve the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Majeſty of the Monarchy, and they will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly do it. And it was nothing but the Craft of ill Men, who kept our late Brinces in continual Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies,
<pb facs="tcp:51025:5"/>of Parliaments, to hold up a Faction for their own Advantage.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, That if upon good Information you find that this is a <hi>mixt Government,</hi> compoſed of the Three Simple Forms, the Enquiring Part belonging more ſpecially to the Commons, the Judiciary to the Lords, the Conſultary and Legiſlative to the King, Lords and Commons, and the Executive to the King, which I believe is the truth, upon this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you look upon the Whole as one great Body, whereof your ſelf is indeed the Head in Honour and Degree, but in effect rather the Hand, or if you will, the Right Hand; but however a Part: And therefore that you always retain a great Reſpect for this Noble Body, treating them with all Honour and Affection, reputing their Honour and Intereſt your own, as Yours is Theirs, and will be ſo treated by them, if a fair Correſpondence be kept up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you; which will make you not only beloved at home, but dreaded abroad.</p>
            <p>Eightly, That you be very tender and cautious of invading <hi>their Rights,</hi> or neglecting <hi>their Counſel,</hi> in any matter of Importance; but eſpecially of holding up any <hi>Favourites</hi> againſt them; and to that end that you be very jealous of that Generation, and thoſe particular Perſons, who have been the Authors or Propagators of <hi>Falſe Notions</hi> concerning the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this Government, or of <hi>Evil Counſels</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51025:5"/>and Courſes among your Predeceſſors; and more eſpecially thoſe, who have already by any <hi>Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> or Unfaithfulneſs in not well informing you, betray'd your ſelf into any Inconvenience: Whereof, if you pleaſe to command me, I ſhall be ready to give you ſome plain Inſtances.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, That you endeavour wiſely <hi>to compoſe the Diſſentions, and allay the Heats and Animoſities of the Nation,</hi> and to unite all in a mutual Aſſiſtance for the Common Intereſt. <hi>Our Diviſions, and the Heats of our Diſſentions,</hi> are for the moſt part the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Popiſh Practices, and Effects of Evil Policies of Courtiers. Theſe have both conſpired for different ends to divide us both in Church and State, and to impoſe upon the People; ſo that it is the trueſt Wiſdom and greateſt Intereſt of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to endeavour ſo much the more for an Union; and to that end to detect their Impoſtures. This Government is in truth a Noble Commonwealth in the Root and Body, accommodated with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and adorned with the Honour and Majeſty of a Monarchy in the Execution. Crafty Men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this, have practis'd the Diviſion in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Firſt, By putting the Kings upon illegal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, till that produced Jealouſies of Arbitrary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and then improving thoſe to the raiſing of the like Jealouſies in thoſe unhappy Kings of Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Conſpiracies. Thus were multitudes impoſed
<pb facs="tcp:51025:6"/>upon: Whereas the Subverſion of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> to ſupport the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> is no leſs Foily, Madneſs and Treachery in an Engliſh Man, than is the pulling down the <hi>Monarchy</hi> to ſupport the <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> Nor can any thing endanger our Monarchs but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by adhering to Evil Counſellors, rejecting or declining the Advice of the Great Council of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and violating their Rights.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That to this purpoſe you avoid all Favour and Encouragement to any Faction; and make no other difference between Perſons, but what the Law hath made; except only between the <hi>Virtuous</hi> and the <hi>Vitious,</hi> and between ſuch as may ſafely be <hi>truſted,</hi> and ſuch as may not, (for which end for Parliament-Men, and perſons admitted to great Offices of Truſt, and Biſhops, a Recognition by Act of Parliament may be neceſſary;) but by a conſtant tenor and courſe of your Actions demonſtrate a cordial and univerſal Affection to All, and a great Zeal and Activity for the Service of God, and for the Peace, Safety and Proſperity of the Nation.</p>
            <p>By theſe Means you will be a compleat King, and rule in the Hearts of the People: Theſe will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in them ſuch a Truſt and Confidence in you, as will make your Government exceeding eaſie; and ſuch a Government will make your Name Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the Roll of our Engliſh Kings: But if you once ſet up for a Separate Intereſt, ſtrike-in
<pb facs="tcp:51025:6"/>with, and make your ſelf the Head of any Faction, give your ſelf up to the Conduct of particular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, ſuffer the Publick Revenue and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Nation to be ſquandred away without any Account, and the People to be injur'd by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions and Delays of Officers, and tread in the ſteps of your Predeceſſors of the laſt Race, you will <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ceaſe to do the part of a King, violate the Truſt repoſed in you, and your Coronation Oath; and deceiving the Expectations of all Men, after ſuch a Succeſſion of Kings, raiſe ſuch Prejudice againſt Monarchy it ſelf, as may indanger this Noble Government, and the Settlement of the Nation, and make your Name inglorious to all Poſterity. But theſe are things ſo inconſiſtent with the Reaſons, for which you was invited hither, the Cauſes of your Expedition expreſſed in your own Declaration, the Ends for which the Crown was firſt offered to you, and after ſet upon your Head, the Honour and Safety of your Government, and, which is more than all, the Righteous Laws of God, (who, as we hope, raiſed you up to be an Inſtrument of Mercy, not of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to This Nation) as no Man, who believes the Character we have received of your great Vertue, can eaſily fear from you, though the notorious Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of the late Reigns may have left ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon the Minds of ſome, which yet I hope Experience of your Prudence and Juſtice will
<pb facs="tcp:51025:7"/>totally expunge. And I pray God give you (as I hope he will) true Wiſdom to know Him, to diſcern His Hand in theſe things, and what He expects from you; to know what is your proper Part in this great Affair, and to be more careful to diſcharge it well, than to enlarge it beyond its juſt Bounds; and that all true Happineſs may always attend your Majeſty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Faithful and, Obedient Subject.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51025:7"/>
            <head>AUTHORITY ABUSED, BY THE Vindication of the Laſt Years <hi>Tranſactions,</hi> AND The ABUSES DETECTED By the Author of the <hi>Reflections.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OF a great many <hi>Evil Arts and Practices,</hi> which in the late Reigns were uſed for the Subverſion of the True Engliſh Government, and Suppreſſion of the moſt ancient common Rights of the People of theſe Nations, one that was moſt conſtantly uſed for that purpoſe, was the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of <hi>Mercenary Writers</hi> to put a colour of Words and Oratory upon thoſe things, for which they had no colour of Law. And it would be a ſad caſe with us, if after ſo glorious a Deliverance, we ſhould be already ſo far deſerted by the Divine Providence, as to ſtand in need of any ſuch Practices or Aſſiſtance: Yet ſo it ſhould ſeem to be, unleſs the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet Entituled, <hi>The laſt Years Tranſactions Vindicated,</hi> be a bold and impudent Impoſture. For it will not be hard to prove, That that Pamphlet is a Falſe, Scandalous and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Libel: And to Print it not only as under <hi>the Patronage</hi> of a Chief Secretary of State, but expreſly as <hi>Publiſhed by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> is either an Act of impudent Impoſture, and a Cheat or Abuſe; or it may be feared we are again relapſing into the ſame unhappy Circumſtances. But I ſuppoſe I ſhall make it appear, that there is <hi>a double Impoſture</hi> in it, that is, That neither had the Writer that Authority for what he did, which was deſign'd he ſhould be thought to have had; nor was it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51025:8"/>deſigned ſincerely to ſerve the Publick Authority of the Nation, the Preſent Government; but to cover the Evil Practices of thoſe Perſons, who were the Authors of our Diſappointments the laſt Year, that they may the better do the like again this. And probably, if the buſineſs be well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, he will be found to have been employed by ſome of them (who are therefore the proper Authors of it) for that end; and not by that Honourable Perſon, whom they have made ſo bold with by this Dedication of <hi>what's written</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>in Defence of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are <hi>three Phraſes</hi> by which uſually the Leave of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for the Publication of Books is briefly expreſſed. The moſt common is <hi>Licenſed;</hi> which ſignifies a written Licenſe under the Hand of ſome Perſon authorized to give it. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>with Allowance,</hi> which implies a Verbal Leave, but of ſome Perſon of great Place and Authority. The third is what the Authors have thought fit to prefix to this Book, <hi>Publiſhed by Authority:</hi> And this (as I take it) implies more than a bare leave, <hi>viz.</hi> Something of a Command, and of ſome great Authority, more than a bare Allowance or Licenſe of a Secretary of State. But what that Authority ſhould be, by which this is publiſhed, I believe will not be eaſie to find or diſcover: Only what it is not will not be difficult to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, even from the conſideration of the Book it ſelf, and divers Paſſages in it.</p>
            <p>Nothing can be ſo truly, innocently, honeſtly and plainly ſaid, but it may be contradicted or oppoſed by a Man of Wit and Parts, with ſome colour and appearance of Reaſon, of which the Oration of <hi>Carneades</hi> againſt Juſtice is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inſtance; and by one, who hath no great ſtore of either, with Railing and Foul Language, of which this Pamphlet we are now conſidering preſents us with a pregnant Inſtance. No leſs than <hi>Folly, Enthuſiaſm, Viſionar, Enthuſiaſtick Illumination, deluded Notion of Inſpiration, Indiſcretion, Excentrick Zeal, Quakers Impulſe,</hi> are all at one Volly let fly at the Author of the Reflections by this mighty Champion, the Vindicator of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51025:8"/>the King, the Parliament, and the whole State at his firſt Charge; all in one Paragraph publiſhed by Authority, if we will believe him; beſides divers ſingle Shots afterwards, as <hi>Silly, precipitant Zeal, hot Politician, Lucid Intervals, Extatick Sermon, Revengeful Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>After ſuch a Charge, it is no wonder to ſee ſuch a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, with no little Oſtentation, inſult over his vanquiſhed Adverſary, and upbraid him with his <hi>confined Sphere, narrow Sphere, ſhort Line, want of Knowledge of Affairs of State, ſmall Skill in Affairs abroad, groſs Ignorance in the Affairs of</hi> Europe, <hi>little Skill in Politicks, none at all in Hiſtory, unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintedneſs with Philoſophy,</hi> and ſuch <hi>groſs miſtakes in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of natural Bodies,</hi> as to believe a moving Cart may be ſtayed by Witchcraft.</p>
            <p>Such ſtuff as this is agreeable enough to the quality of a Mercenary Writer, a temporizing Obſervator, a Mountebank, a Quack, and might have paſſed with ſome ordinary Licencers: But as it doth never advantage any Cauſe, ſo it is uſually a ſign of either a very barren Cauſe, or a very ſhallow brain, where it is much uſed without any Proof or Reaſon: And therefore Men in great Authority, do rarely imploy ſuch Writers, or if they do, do it only by ſome <hi>Secret Encouragement,</hi> not by any <hi>Publick Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this general conſideration be not ſufficient to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Authors ſuſpected of Impoſture in that reſpect, the Writer himſelf hath ſupplied us in the very next Page with ſpecial matter to help it out, telling us that <hi>the King by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy of good Nature has laid aſide the Reſentment ſuch a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet would have met with in any Reign but His:</hi> And if this be not yet enough, he immediately adds his own Sentence of Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemnation: <hi>And where the King forgives, its ill manners to ſtint the Royal Bounty by ill Treating the Griminal.</hi> For if any one beſides this Champion would be guilty of ſuch ill manners, it ought not certainly to be believed that any one near the King, or of any great Authority would by Publickly Authorizing it: Much leſs that ſo ill a treatment ſhould be Authorized by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51025:9"/>that Noble Lord to whom they have preſumed to Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it. Sure I am he had no great reaſon to do it, if he <hi>acted</hi> any <hi>great part</hi> in the Tranſactions, and the Vindication be <hi>written in Defence of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is here inferred from the <hi>Modeſty and Decency of the Terms and Language,</hi> may likewiſe be inferred from the <hi>Truth and Honeſty of the Suggeſtions, Aſſertions, and Inferences.</hi> It would be too long to examine all, and beſides needleſs: I will therefore for brevity ſake only confront three or four of the Aſſertions with the words of the Reflections; and leave the Reader to conſider how proper and likely ſuch Candor and Ingenuity is to be Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. He chargeth the Author of the Reflections, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Daniſh Forces, with <hi>
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Aſſerting plainly</hi> They will prove a greater Burthen than Advantage to us.</hi> Whereas the words of the Reflections are only thus. <hi>The Seaſon of the year is now far gon, that they are <hi>more like</hi> to prove a Burden <hi>this <hi rend="blackletterType">Winter,</hi>
                  </hi> than any Advantage to us.</hi> And this is called a Calumny, <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. but with how great reaſon the Reader may there ſee.</p>
            <p>Again in the ſame, <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. reciting the words of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections concerning our Loſſes at Sea, he concludes Speaking of the Author, that He <hi>
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">boldly adde,</hi> That our Merchants Ships have been made a prey to thoſe who ſhould have been their Guide and Convey.</hi> Whereas the Reflections inſted of <hi>holdly adding</hi> what he ſaith, <hi>cautiouſly premiſe</hi> a Parentheſis, which this honeſt and candid Gentleman was ſo bold as to leave out. viz. <hi>(If the Complaints of our Merchants and their Mariners be true.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But never did our Champion behave himſelf more bravely and like himſelf than when he comes to talk of <hi>the Abdication.</hi> That one Paragraph of the Reflections makes him lay about him indeed like a Man of mettle, for three Paragraphs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: It ſeems he was not a little concerned at it; and where the Concern lay is not hard to be perceived. But here I ſhall only take notice of one inſtance more for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, leaving the reſt to the Readers obſervation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51025:9"/>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 21. he tells us: <hi>Our new Politician is downright offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Parliament for finding King</hi> Jame's <hi>Departure an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Government, &amp;c.</hi> This certainly is no leſs than a piece of Jeſuitical Modeſty, where-ever this Traveller learnt it. The words of the Reflections are down right the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: <hi>There was reaſon enough to declare the departure of King</hi> James <hi>under his circumſtances an Abdication of the Government, &amp;c.</hi> And this is not only ſaid, but ſo cleared and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there in few lines, as hath given no little Satisfaction to ſome perſons of no mean parts and learning; but no leſs Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance, (it ſeems) to this Gentleman, as may be farther noted hereafter.</p>
            <p>Another Aſſertion or two I muſt take notice of, for the <hi>ſingular Charity</hi> expreſſed in them. Thoſe, as they are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and cannot be deduced by any good Inference from the Reflections, ſo may they be confronted with other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the ſame Authors in print: <hi>This Man</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of the Author of the Reflections) <hi>would drench the World in Blood, Sacrifice whole Hecatombs to his Revenge, and once more ſet theſe Kingdoms off their Hinges by a precipitate Method of rendring Men deſperate,</hi> Page 21. Such another is the Suggeſtion, <hi>page</hi> 22. <hi>Why ſhould King</hi> James'<hi>s Miniſters and Counſellors, <hi rend="blackletterType">all of them, without diſtinction,</hi> fall under the ſtroak?</hi> And again, <hi>page</hi> 23. <hi>Our Author fondly concludes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>becauſe he hath not been glutted with the Blood of the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents.</hi> I need note no more of this kind. Thoſe are ſo foul and infamous Words, that if written and publiſhed without very good grounds, do of themſelves ſufficiently make good one part of my Charge againſt this Pamphlet. Certain I am, that no ſuch thing was ever intended in the Reflections: And from theſe Words in the Paragraph under his conſideration, <hi>
                  <hi>Not one</hi> of thoſe, who by their wicked Counſels and Compliances betrayed not only their Country, but their King himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hath yet been brought to condign Puniſhment,</hi> or from any other in that Book, I do not ſee how any ſuch matter can be dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: But if confronted with what the ſame Author hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51025:10"/>written in his Apology for Mr. <hi>Stafford,</hi> page 17. and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, it will all there appear as falſe, as here it doth groundleſs.</p>
            <p>What hath been already noted, I ſuppoſe, is ſufficient to make good the Charge of a Falſe and Infamous Libel. The <hi>Piety</hi> of it may be diſcerned by the Reſpect therin given to the Sacred Scriptures, where he ſaith, that the Expreſſions, <hi>Taught of God, Children of Light, Senſual not having the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and many others of that kind, ſmell of the late delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Notion of Inſpiration, <hi>page</hi> 2. and by the regard therein expreſſed to the Providence of God, and to the Study and Conſideration of his Works and Dealings with the Sons of Men, <hi>pag.</hi> 26. and by the Reproachful Terms, which, after the mode of the late Atheiſtical Times, are very confidently beſtowed upon ſincere Piety, and genuine Religion. But I have no mind to caſt Pearles before Swine, by a full Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of theſe things; but leaving him, and ſuch <hi>Abderites</hi> to the Correction of ſome <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> ſhall content my ſelf with thoſe Evangelical Promiſes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.11, 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. and rejoyce in them too, while the Mercenary Writer may chance to feel the ſmart of his own Prophaneneſs, in ſelling his Conſcience for a Meſs of Pottage.</p>
            <p>And now to return to our Enquiry, <hi>What Authority it ſhould be, which hath ordered the Publication of ſuch a Libel?</hi> Of the King we are ſecure, that it was not he, by what hath been recited before; and of the Parliament, were we not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſecure, this Writer hath given us the like aſſurance, telling us, <hi>He knows not but he may be blameable in playing the Advocate, or in daring to ſuppoſe, that the great Council of the Nation needs a Vindication,</hi> page 16. And the ſame we may conclude, for the ſame Reaſon, of that Noble Lord, whoſe Patronage he thinks but reaſon he (ſhould) allow to <hi>what's written in defence of others.</hi> It remains then, that either he had none at all, and then he is an Impoſtor upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; or that it was from ſome of thoſe <hi>others,</hi> in whoſe Defence it was written, and then is he no leſs an Impoſtor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51025:10"/>in concealing whoſe it was, and giving occaſion by this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication to make that Noble Perſon be believed, by inob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant Readers, to be the Man. And this we have reaſon to believe is the Truth, if the Scope and divers Paſſages of this Vindication be well conſidered.</p>
            <p>It is true, he pretends much Zeal and Concern for the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the King, and of the Parliament; but that is no more than every Knave and Cheat will do to thoſe he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to abuſe; the <hi>Officious Kiſſes of an Enemy;</hi> and therefore whether ſincere, or feigned, is to be determined by the concurrence of other Indications. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. It appears by his own ſhewing, that he is a very offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Advocate, and was never retained or imployed by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor was there much cauſe of Vindication in reſpect of either of them; for moſt of the Tranſactions noted, were reflected on as matters of Diſappointments and Unhappineſs, rather than Faults in them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And theſe Diſappointments being imputed not only by the Author of the Reflections, but by the Parliament it ſelf, to the unfaithfulneſs and Treachery of Perſons intruſted and imployed, the Vindication of ſuch Tranſactions could not be ſincerely intended to ſerve the King, or gratifie the Parliament, but to cover thoſe Evil Practices and Perſons, which not only the Author of the Reflections, but the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament alſo, deſired and endeavoured to diſcover.</p>
            <p>And that this was really the <hi>Deſign</hi> of this Mercenary Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, whoever had their Hands in it, and all the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the King, the Parliament, and the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> Principal Secretary of State, a meer Diſguiſe to cover that Deſign, and an Abuſe upon that Noble Perſon at leaſt, there are divers Obſervables in it perſwade me to believe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The very Beginning diſcovers his Mind, and what he was full of. It is a <hi>Severe Cenſure againſt prying too narrowly into the Secrets of Government and Myſteries of State:</hi> But if the Reflections be well conſidered, there is no other occaſion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51025:11"/>for it but Honeſt Endeavours for ſuch a Diſcovery, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, that is, of what his buſineſs was to cover.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He there alſo diſcovers, or to uſe his own term, bewrays himſelf to be a genuine Diſciple of the Mercenary Writers of the late Reigns, by <hi>magnifying the Policy of a Foreign State,</hi> as if our Laws were defective; only he ſhews himſelf but a Novice in the Trade, in that he takes his Precedent from <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,</hi> and not from <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</hi> Of his ſenſe of the Engliſh Conſtitution I ſhall take notice hereafter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And he preſently after diſcovers his Affection <hi>to the Engliſh Nation,</hi> which he more than once, without any juſt occaſion that appears, terms <hi>an ungrateful Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. He bewrays himſelf indeed, and diſcovers his rotten and <hi>unſound Notions and Sentiments concerning our preſen Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Bight of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to the Gevernment of theſe Kingdoms: And that he himſelf is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one of that Mungrel Temporizing Party, which hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed our compleat Settlement and underhand retarded the Reduction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or at leaſt doth proſtitute his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Pen to gratify that Party.</p>
            <p>For he plainly unhinges King <hi>Williams Title,</hi> and ſets it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a falſe bottom, while he makes King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Abdication</hi> to conſiſt only, in his Departure. This is it which he finds fault with in the Reflections, that they do not admit the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of King <hi>James</hi> to be an Abdication, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his precedent Actions. And that this is his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth farther appear by his quarrelling the Author for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting the Departure to be <hi>rather the flight of a Criminal from Juſtice, than of an innocent Man; Metus cauſâ &amp; cum animo reverlendi.</hi> And this being ſo, it cannot proceed but either from a diſhoneſt Mind, and an ill deſign to undermine the Juſtice of the preſent King's Title, or from Ignorance: For no good Author ever yet called the Flight of an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Man <hi>Metus cauſa,</hi> an Abdication. And becauſe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended great Learning and Reading of Hiſtory will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51025:11"/>us to believe the latter, he can blame no body but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if we impute it to the former; And the Truth is, I ſee not how he can avoid that imputation: For if he really thinks what is there ſaid, to be <hi>a ſevere inſinuation againſt the late King,</hi> and that <hi>no Kings are to be brought to Juſtice,</hi> he is a temporizing Perſon, to comply and flatter a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment erected upon no better ground than a pretended Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication: But if he really believes the grounds upon which the Convocation declared that Departure an Abdication (which were that Kings precedent Actions) to be good, then is he baſely <hi>Mercenary,</hi> to diſſemble his own Opinion in compliance with ſome of that mungrel Party, who are ſtill for a <hi>Regency.</hi> And this Government can never be ſafe while ſuch Perſons are permitted to have acceſs to any Office of Secretary of State.</p>
            <p>My Principles I had publiſhed in Print long ſince in the <hi>Important Queſtions,</hi> and again lately, but before his Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet came to the Preſs, in an Apology for Mr. <hi>Stafford,</hi> and therefore had no Maſque of my own for him to remove: But I hope I have by this time taken off one from him, and ſhall preſently take off another; for I doubt not, but this Leaf and the firſt Leaf of the next Sheet contain the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of thoſe Perſons, in whoſe Defence, this Maſque call'd a Vindication, was Written, and by whoſe Authority it was Publiſhed. It was not the King, nor the Parliament, nor the Principal Secretary of State, for whom this Service was deſigned: It was <hi>Written in the Defence of others;</hi> and who thoſe <hi>others</hi> were, we may here perceive plainly enough. They are of Three ſorts;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Regency-men,</hi> thoſe who were principally deſigned to be gratified in the Paragraph laſt mentioned, and indeed in the whole undertaking.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>King</hi> James<hi>'s Counſellors, Agents, and Accomplices,</hi> to be exempt from condign Puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. One or Two <hi>in King</hi> Charles<hi>'s Reign, wrought upon through the Temptations and Snares of a Court;</hi> and ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51025:12"/>Perſons, <hi>who in either of the Two laſt Reigns, had ſtumbled upon unwarrantable Meaſures;</hi> and theſe are to be received into Favour.</p>
            <p>There is one ſort more they ſhould alſo have put in, had it not been too groſs a matter to have been mentioned at this time, and that is <hi>the French Kings Penſioners;</hi> who, there is reaſon to believe, had not left off their old trade in the Tranſactions of the laſt Year; but there are none of them but may be comprehended among ſome of theſe here ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified. And as theſe plainly were deſigned to be ſerved by this Pamphlet, ſo I doubt not but ſome of theſe ſet the Work on foot, and were the contrivers of its Dedication to the chief Secretary of State, and are therefore properly the chief Authors of it. <hi>Qui facit per alium, eſt perinde ac ſi faciat per ſeipſum c. qui facit de reg. jur.</hi> 6. As for <hi>the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon imployed to write it,</hi> it ſeemed very apparent to me in the peruſal, to be in divers paſſages a mere perſonated buſineſs, and to be written <hi>invita Minerva,</hi> and which is worſe, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctante Conſcientia;</hi> which when I obſerved, it moved ſo much plty in me, that I preſently ſtruck out ſuch paſſages as would too plainly have diſcovered him, and I thought too ſevere for a man in ſuch a caſe; and I heartily pray God give him Repentance, and forgive him. But for <hi>thoſe who imployed him</hi> (for that he wrote it not of himſelf, but was put upon it by ſome others, is but a natural conſequence of what I have ſaid) we may plainly diſcover ſomething of their Character, by this Vindication.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is plain that they are <hi>men of Craft and Tricks;</hi> for this is plainly a trick put upon the Chief Secretary of State, to make the World believe that he was concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and if they were ſo bold with him, the King himſelf may have reaſon to look about him, leſt he be trick'd by them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They muſt be ſuch as had ſome conſiderable <hi>concern in the pretended Vindication,</hi> and acted a great and notable (not noble) part in the Tranſactions, that is, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51025:12"/>or mediately in our Diſappointments; a much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent part from what was acted by the Noble Perſon whom they craftily apply to, as one concerned by participation in the ſame actions with themſelves; and undoubtedly will be apt to play the like tricks with the King himſelf if they can, by putting him upon ſuch actions as may juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at leaſt, and ſo engage him to ſtand by them in their ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal practices, an Artifice, by which the laſt race of our Kings have been often abuſed, and not yet forgotten.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What I have before obſerved of the Writer, muſt be true alſo of the principal Authors; nay more certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true of them, whom he deſigned to pleaſe: For whatever was his own Opinion, it was accomodated to the Sentiments of them who imploy'd him, and therefore they muſt <hi>be men of no good Opinion of this Government,</hi> nor cordial Friends to the preſent King and Queen; ſo that this and my laſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation do mutually confirm each other.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Nor are they men of very ſound <hi>notions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true Engliſh Conſtitution and Government,</hi> as may be collected from their ſlighting expreſſions, uſed upon what in the Reflections is obſerved concerning the Privy Council and ſecret Cabals, calling it <hi>the Authors Eutopean Model,</hi> and from ſome expreſſions let fall concerning the Calling and Diſſolving of Parliaments, of which more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thus much of their Character may be eaſily and plainly perceived by this Maſque, which they call a Vindication; But becauſe it is a matter of no ſmall importance to the preſent King and Queen, and to the Peace and Happineſs of theſe Nations, for our quiet Enjoyment of the admirable Mercy which Almighty God hath ſo graciouſly conferred upon us, and for our better improvement of the Advantage he hath put into our hands, that theſe Perſons, who by their Craft and evil Deſigns, have occaſioned our former diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, may be more fully detected, to prevent greater miſchief for the future; I ſhall endeavour to explain ſome of thoſe <hi>Myſterious practices,</hi> which are <hi>uſed at this day,</hi> from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51025:13"/>their very Original, in the days of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; and then return to what is neceſſary to be further obſerved upon this Vindication.</p>
            <p>When that King after that horrid Plot of the Gunpowder Treaſon, being more terrified with the Danger he had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, than animated by ſo great a Deliverance, to depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Providence of God who preſerved him, which that Deliverance in a ſpecial manner obliged him to; deſerting that great Duty, and relying upon his own craft, ſought to ſecure himſelf and his own Poſterity, by Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Alliances with his Enemies, <hi>the Papiſts,</hi> like thoſe who have recourſe to Witches and Conjurers; inſtead of that Security he expected, he involved himſelf and his Poſterity in ſuch Snares, as were the real cauſe of all thoſe Evils which afterward befel them, and out of which they could never after extricate themſelves. During the long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who generouſly performing that great Duty, kept them at a diſtance; all they could do was only to contrive ſecret Plots againſt her Perſon, and Foreign Invaſions, and to ſow Seeds of Diviſion in ſecret Meetings, all which that Providence of God, in which ſhe confided, diſſipated and turned to their own Confuſion. But when afterward they were favoured and admitted to a nearer Converſe with our Princes, Stateſmen and Biſhops, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently found their Advantage to put in practice <hi>other Policies of a more deep, ſubtile, and dangerous Nature,</hi> and under the cover of very plauſible Pretences, whereby they and their Venome might inſinuate the deeper. Theſe were princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally Three; 1. To change the Government, and make it Arbitrary and Abſolute in the Prince. 2. To raiſe and heighten Diviſions. 3. To corrupt the Manners of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To endeavour a <hi>Change of the Government,</hi> they ſaw ſeveral Reaſons. 1. They plainly ſaw it to be utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable to deal with the other two Eſtates, to introduce their Religion. 2. They alſo underſtood very well that ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51025:13"/>endeavours might be ſo managed as to ingratiate them with the Prince, and many of the Courtiers, Miniſters of State, and of the aſpiring Clergy. 3. They alſo foreſaw, that by ſlighly inſinuating into the Prince, and his Favourites and Flatterers, ſuch matters as tended to this; they ſhould alſo by the ſame means promote their other deſign of raiſing Diviſions between the Prince and the People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To raiſe and heighten <hi>Diviſions,</hi> they eaſily ſaw would not only weaken and diſſolve the ſtrength of the Nation, but would alſo give them a fair opportunity to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under one Party or other, as they ſhould ſee occaſion. Theſe Advantages they might expect by Civil Diſſentions; and theſe and ſome more by Diviſions alſo about matters of Religion, and therefore they induſtriouſly promoted both.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And to <hi>corrupt the manners of the Nation,</hi> they might expect would give them theſe Advantages, 1. It would weaken the ſtrength of the Nation, making men more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and careleſs of any Publick Concern, and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them for either Prudent Counſel or Generous Action. 2. It would make them more indifferent in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and leſs apt to give them any diſturbance in the proſecution of their Deſigns. 3. And this indifference would diſpoſe them to the more eaſie admiſſion of theirs when it ſhould be ſeaſonably and prudently propoſed to them under ſome plauſible pretences.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the Principal of their <hi>Policies,</hi> and the <hi>Grounds</hi> of them; which were rational enough, though it pleaſed God, who hath the Hearts of all Men at his diſpoſal, by his over-ruling Providence, in his own time, to defeat them all. But the <hi>Contrivances, Methods, and particular Practices,</hi> which they uſed for the promotion of theſe Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Deſigns, were too many to be here diſcovered; nor is that my buſineſs at this time. I ſhall therefore only take notice of ſuch as are pertinent to the preſent occaſion, that is, <hi>ſuch as aſpiring Courtiers and Clergymen joyned with them in,</hi> though for different ends of their own, and ſuch as we have ſtill reaſon to beware of: Such as theſe;</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51025:14"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Magnifying the Regal Power</hi> upon falſe Principles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its true bounds, according to the Engliſh Conſtitution, and <hi>Vilifying our Laws</hi> in general, as rude and barbarous; and the Fundamentals of our Conſtitution, which limit and reſtrain the Exceſſes of Regal Power, as encroachments of the People upon Prerogative, and ſo poſſeſſing the King and many honeſt welmeaning People, not ſufficiently acquainted with the Excellence of our Laws and Conſtitutions, with <hi>Falſe, Dangerous, and Pernicious Notions concerning our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> And having by this means prepared the way, and inſinuated themſelves into Favour, they never failed of ſome <hi>Project</hi> for their own ends, though never ſo illegal, to put the King upon encouraging him to deſpiſe the juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the People, as clamours, and that which was below his Majeſty to be aw'd by. And becauſe this could not but move all truly Loyal, honeſt and underſtanding Men, who ſaw the dangerous Conſequences to the King, as well as to the People, of ſuch Courſes; it was very natural and eaſie to them to repreſent all ſuch as Perſons of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical and Republican Principles. And always by how much the more notorious and illegal were their Practices, by ſo much the greater and lowder were the clamours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Commonwealth Principles, and the noiſe of the Dangers threatning the Monarchy. And by this means were our Kings kept in continual Jealouſie and ill Opinion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their beſt, moſt honeſt, Loyal and moſt faithful Subjects.</p>
            <p>But they could never have proceeded ſo far in theſe things had they not by inculcating falſe Notions concerning one branch of the Regal Office, <hi>the Calling, Proroguing, and Diſſolving of Parliaments,</hi> and ſuggeſting falſe Fears and Dangers of the conſequence of their Sitting, often prevailed with thoſe Kings to abuſe the Truſt, in that reſpect repoſed in them, contrary to the Conſtitution of this Government, to the moſt ancient Laws of this Nation, to the true intent and meaning of the Statutes, then and ſtill in Force, and to their own true intereſt and ſafety, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51025:14"/>
            <p>By theſe means were our <hi>Civil Diſſentions</hi> begun, and by degrees continually heightened, till by theſe Practices, and the like, in matters of Religion, in the Year <hi>Forty one,</hi> they involved the King in <hi>a Civil War</hi> to make good thoſe illegal Practices, which they before had engaged him in, and by conſequence in an ill Cauſe, againſt as good a Parliament, as perhaps this Nation ever had. This will ſeem ſtrange to ſome to come from me, who was from my Youth on the Kings ſide, and at Fifteen Years of Age ventured my life for his Service. But I know what I ſay, and will preſently make it clear. The King might have truſted that Parliament, they would never have hurt him, or diminiſhed any thing of his true Prerogative, but have ſecured him and it againſt the Abuſes put upon him and the whole Nation, by evil Men, under pretence of it, if he durſt but have trueſted them. This is very plain from the Prevalence of that part of the Parliament, which, although the King had withdrawn ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part to <hi>Oxford,</hi> which would certainly have joyned with them, were yet able to carry the Vote, <hi>That the Kings Conceſſions were Satisfactory:</hi> Nor were that part, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward brought the King to his Tryal, able to have carried any thing againſt him, had they not firſt by Force, which had never been raiſed, had not the King been carried away by his criminal Favorites, ſecluded moſt of the Principal men of the other part. But though the King might have truſted them, yet were there thoſe about him, who conſcious of their own guilt, having been the evil Counſellors and Promoters of thoſe illegal Practices, which occaſioned the War, durſt not ſtand the Tryal; and therefore, having firſt betrayed him into thoſe miſchiefs before mentioned, betrayed him now a ſecond time, by withdrawing him for their own ſecurity from the Parliament, and with him divers Members of both Houſes, who would have been more ſerviceable there both to him and to the Kingdom, and ſo at length in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved him in that fatal Civil War, for their own defence, which brought him to that unhappy end. Theſe were <hi>the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51025:15"/>true Authors of that War;</hi> and theſe are the <hi>Forty one Men,</hi> who deſerve to be remembred with no leſs deteſtation by all Poſterity, than thoſe of Forty eight, who only finiſhed what the others had begun. This I have related the more largely, becauſe I ſee the ſame wicked Practices carried on by the Ringleaders of thoſe, who have <hi>Forty one</hi> much in their Mouths; and they who are not ſatisfied with may Reaſon, may ſee it, if they pleaſe, confirmed by Authority of King and Parliament, in the Preamble of the <hi>Act of Attainder,</hi> 12. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Methods for raiſing and heightning the <hi>Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the Church,</hi> were firſt by improving the Prejudices which King <hi>James</hi> had conceived againſt ſome Zealots in <hi>Scotland,</hi> into like prejudice, firſt againſt the Puritans in <hi>England,</hi> then againſt all truly Religious and Conſcientious People, as Puritans and Preciſians; and at laſt againſt all who diſcovered any great warmth againſt Popery. By this means Formality and Indifference in Religion was brought into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion and encouraged, and ſincere Religion and Devotion ſlighted and diſcountenanced: And for this purpoſe was <hi>the Book of Sports</hi> upon the Lords day ſet out, and ordered to be Read in Churches, and many good men put out of their Livings for refuſing to Read it. And when by theſe means, Formality and Popery being favoured, and ſincere Religion not only ſlighted, but oppreſſed contrary to Law, diſcontents could not but riſe; theſe were again made uſe of to repreſent the beſt part of the Nation as ill affected to Monarchy and the Church, becauſe they began to be ſenſible of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of Tyranny and Popery, and of the over-ſpeading of Formality. And this is <hi>the true Original of the great outcries, The Monarchy, <hi rend="blackletterType">and</hi> The Church</hi> being in danger, (as indeed they were, but the one of degenerating into Tyranny, and the other into mear Formality, if not Popery) whereby multitudes were impoſed upon to put their helping hands to overturn both one way, while they were craftily made believe, that others were doing it the other; for theſe had their influence in producing the late Civil War in conjunction with thoſe before mentioned.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51025:15"/>
            <p n="3">3. By the ſame means was the Foundation laid for the <hi>Corruption of the Manners</hi> of the Nation: But by what Means and Methods that was promoted before the Kings Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and afterward rais'd to that height in his Reign, is not much to my preſent purpoſe, though we feel the ill effects thereof, and are ſtill like to do ſo, if they be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>The Diſmal <hi>Conſequences of theſe things</hi> to the King, to the Church, and to the whole Nation, ſad Experience at length taught her careleſs and inconſiderate Scholars, who diſregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the milder and ſafer Admonition of Provident Wiſdom: And though the Effects and Conſequences were ſuch, as one would think ſhould not eaſily or quickly be forgotten; yet becauſe the Practices and Cauſes are ſo little underſtood or conſidered by a great part of the Nation, that they ſeem diſpoſed to be as much impoſed upon again, and run into the like Confuſions, to this brief and plain Narrative I will add ſome few <hi>Obſervations</hi> to ſtop the Current, and give ſome warning againſt the Danger.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, To ſuch as have any Senſe of Religion, and Acquaintance with the Works and Methods of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, it will not be hard to perceive, That <hi>the Original of all thoſe Evils,</hi> in which King <hi>James</hi> involved himſelf and his Family, was his <hi>Deſerting of that great Duty</hi> of Truſt and Conſidence in, and firm Dependance upon that Providence, which had with ſo much caſe and ſafety brought him to the Throne of theſe Kingdoms beyond his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and given him ſo great an Experiment of its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, by ſo amazing a Deliverance from ſo great and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent a Danger, and applying himſelf to vain worldly Wiſdom, in ſeeking Security by Compliance and Alliances with Enemies; thoſe very Enemies, from whoſe ſubtile Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations he had been ſo admirably delivered; and proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting his Religion to thoſe Politicks, which was ſomewhat of Kin to the Sin of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> which ſtuck ſo cloſe to his Houſe.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51025:16"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The immediate Evil,</hi> which he and his Family thereby incurred, was <hi>a moſt juſt and ſuitable Puniſhment, viz.</hi> To be deſerted by that Providence, which he firſt deſerted, and be given up <hi>Rehoboam</hi>-like to the evil and pernicious Counſels of thoſe flattering and deceitful Favourites, whom they choſe and adhered to. This was one and a ſpecial part of the <hi>Fate of the Family,</hi> out of which they never extricated themſelves, though they had divers fair Opportunities, and very cogent Motives offered to them, to have done it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That which expoſed him and them the more to this Fate, and intangled them the deeper therein, was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable <hi>Deſire and Affectation of an abſolute Dominion,</hi> which was not ſo much ſatisfied, as inlarged by the Acceſſion of thoſe two Crowns of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> to his former one of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and a certain <hi>Degeneracy of mind,</hi> the uſual effect of unjuſtifiable Actions, or inſincere Deſigns, which made them neglect the Legal Privy Council, and avoid the Preſence of Parliaments, as People in a Fault do the ſight of their beſt Friends, till ſome neceſſity conſtrain them. And this gave Opportunity and Encouragement to thoſe Evil Counſellors to entangle them more and more in illegal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Practices; which made them ſo much the more afraid of Parliaments, to whom it belongs to enquire and conſider of ſuch matters, and adhere the faſter to thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, till they became ſo united to them, that they thought themſelves ſtruck at in whatever was done or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This made them eaſie to be perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it was their Prerogative to <hi>Call, and Prorogue, and Diſſolve Parliaments at their own Pleaſure;</hi> and accordingly to do it, in effect at the pleaſure, that is, at the perſwaſion of thoſe Favourites: Whereas not only the Notion is falſe, and ſet up only for the Advantage of Favourites and Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals; but the Practice was doubly miſchievous to the Kings themſelves. For 1. It was a great cauſe of Diſcontent, heightned the Differences between the King and the People,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51025:16"/>and made the Kings Cauſe ſo much the worſe in thoſe Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and unjuſtifiable, being often times a wilful and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>refuſal of Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Protection of Criminals</hi> againſt the whole Nation. 2. It deprived the King, as well as the People, of the proper Remedy of thoſe Miſchiefs. For Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments are the great Security under God of Kings from Abuſes, as well as of the People from Oppreſſion; and the Perſons were either Guilty, or Not Guilty: If Guilty, they ought to be try'd, and either ſuffer according to their Crimes; or, if there were any ſpecial reaſon for it, be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd. If not Guilty, yet ought they to be try'd, that their Innocence might be cleared, and the Nation ſatisfy'd.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The ſame may be obſerv'd concerning the great <hi>Noiſe</hi> that was made of <hi>the Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>the Church,</hi> as if both were deſign'd to be preſently deſtroyed; which were nothing but falſe Clamours to incenſe People, and raiſe a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by the Inſtigation of thoſe evil Men for their own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and defence againſt Juſtice. The juſt Puniſhment of Criminals, who betrayed both King and People, was the Deſtruction of Monarchy, and Reformation of the manners of the Clergy, the Subverſion of the Church, in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. But by theſe means were a great many honeſt well-meaning People impos'd upon, and a mighty Faction rais'd. Whereas it is certain, that the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy,</hi> being not meerly an Honorary matter, but of great Uſe and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the whole Nation both at home and abroad, if it be not abuſed, the People and their Repreſentatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have always ſo well underſtood their Intereſt therein, and do ſo at this day; that nothing but ſome extraordinary matter ever could, or can alienate their Affections from it. This is plain in the caſe of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. when notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Provocations which are ſet out in the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the State of the Kingdom,</hi> 15 <hi>Dec.</hi> 1642. and ſome others, that Parliament would neither have deſtroyed the Monarchy, nor hurt the King, (though out of thoſe Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions a violent Party was rais'd, which did both) nor would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51025:17"/>the Nation after be quiet till his Son was reſtored. And for <hi>the Church,</hi> the Biſhops and Eccleſiaſtical Courts, might have been quiet, had they been truly Chriſtian, as they would be called. But that, which moved the Indignation of moſt underſtanding and honeſt Men againſt them, was to ſee Chriſtianity prophan'd, and Offices of Religion ſought and uſed as Secular Employments; to ſee Formality encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, ſincere Piety (though perhaps mixt with ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Scrupuloſity) oppreſſed, and the Miniſters of the Righteous Kingdom of Chriſt turn Promoters of Arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Tyranny. And it is no wonder if ſuch Cauſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch Effects.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, It was <hi>the raiſing and heightning of that Faction</hi> by the Favourites and Criminal Party, that <hi>brought things to that Extremity of a War,</hi> which otherwiſe might have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and all ſatisfy'd with the Removal of a few Evil Men from about the King, the Puniſhment of a few Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and the Reformation of a few neceſſary things. But while theſe Evil Counſellors and Favourites raiſed that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for the ſecurity of themſelves under the pretence of the King and the Church, they thereby laid the Foundation of the real Deſtruction of both for ſome time. And I wiſh all honeſt Men may take warning by it now, and not ſuffer themſelves to be impos'd upon again after ſuch an Example. For there is <hi>Juſt ſuch another Faction,</hi> which hath gone very high of late, eſpecially in the buſineſs of Elections under the ſame Pretences of <hi>the Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>the Church,</hi> wherein the greateſt Sticklers were thoſe ſort of Perſons, which the Vindicators of the laſt years Tranſactions recommend to Favour, that is, the Criminals of the two laſt Reigns, the Counſellors, Agents and Accomplices of King <hi>James,</hi> and the Regency-men and <hi>Haeſitators,</hi> who refuſe to act under King <hi>William,</hi> with whom the Papiſts joyned under-hand. And their greateſt Oppoſition was for the moſt part againſt ſuch as were moſt Cordial and Active for the preſent King and Queen.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51025:17"/>
            <p>I have but one thing more to obſerve, which comes now into my mind, and hath not been ſo well conſidered as it ought; and that is the great and miſchievous Influence, which ſuch <hi>prodigal and unadviſed conferring of Honours,</hi> as was begun by King <hi>James</hi> I. and has been continued fince, is apt to have in the producing of ſuch Troubles. <hi>Honor and Riches</hi> are things, which may be of good uſe for the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of others, when they fall to the ſhare of Good Men, who have Hearts to make uſe of them for that purpoſe. But I very much doubt, whether ever any Man was the better for them? On the contrary it is apparent, that many, nay moſt, are the worſe for them, if they be raiſed much above their own Rank. And it is certain that they are no good Men, who are very greedy of either; but ſuch as will comply with the Means, whereby they are to be obtained, be they what they will. If the Prince, who hath the diſpoſing of Honors and Preferments, be wiſe and vertuous, be ſparing and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in conferring them only upon conſideration of Worth and Merit; it will be an effectual means to incline the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to apply themſelves to ſuch means, which will be of great advantage to the Commonwealth. But if he be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal and inconſiderate in the diſpoſing of them, he will not fail to attract to him many ill Men of no vertue, who will certainly flatter and deceive him; make it their buſineſs to pleaſe him for their own advantage, at any rate, rather than faithfully ſerve him. And the more Honours he confers upon ſuch, the greater Burden he thereby brings upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: He muſt provide for his own Creatures; and if he hath not good and lawful means to provide for them, they will not fail of Projects even of indirect means by him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for themſelves. Beſides, the Appetite is unſatiable: The Man's no more ſatisfy'd when made a Lord, than when but a Knight; I'm ſure not more happy; nor when made an Earl, than when but a Baron; nor when made a Marques, than when but an Earl; but a Baron, but a Knight, but a private Gentleman. But he needs more; his Needs are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51025:18"/>and muſt be ſupplied one way or other. And from this Root did ſpring many of thoſe Illegal Projects in the Reigns of King <hi>James</hi> I. and King <hi>Charles</hi> I. which in the end produced thoſe bitter Fruits we have been ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p>And now to return to our merciful Vindicator. He makes me think of the vulgar Obſervation of <hi>March,</hi> that it comes in like a Lion, and goes out like a Lamb; and he ſhews himſelf a right <hi>March Bird.</hi> Our Laws were not ſevere enough with him at the beginning to puniſh the Author of the Reflections, whom yet he dares not charge with any <hi>want of kindneſs to his Majeſty, v. p.</hi> 2. But he muſt fetch a Precedent as far as <hi>Venice,</hi> to ſhew the heinouſneſs of his Crimes in prying into Secrets of State, to be no leſs than what is puniſhable with Death. But when he comes to King <hi>James</hi>'s Counſellors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how is the Lion changed into the Lamb! But alas! it is only to thoſe good People. So kind to them, that one would think that this Vindicator had had ſome hand in the Letter and Bill of Pardon for King <hi>James,</hi> which was found in the Speakers Chair. But to the Author of the Reflections he preſently turns Lion again, at leaſt puts on the Lions Skin. If he but complain for the juſt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Aſſertion of our preſent Settlement, that not one of King <hi>James's</hi> Inſtruments has been brought to condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; how does this Lion roar and ſtorm at this as a <hi>Revengeful Spirit,</hi> that <hi>would drench the World in Blood!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, it ſeems but a Copy of his Countenance, a meer perſonated Fury to pleaſe ſome body. But what their Sentiments are, who were to be pleaſed with this, is not hard to be underſtood. They were, it ſeems, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Pardon, but for Preferment too, for thoſe honeſt Gentlemen, as ſuch as <hi>do deſerve the return of our Gratitude.</hi> Sure this Writer had a mind to try his Skill in Oratory, and after the Example of <hi>Carneades,</hi> try what he could add to his Oration againſt Juſtice. And I ſhould have thought that <hi>Carneades</hi> had got a new Set of Scholars amongſt us, ſince the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51025:18"/>late Revolution. For ſince I wrote the laſt Period, I met with another <hi>Vindication</hi> ſo like this, that I dare preſume the Authors of both are pretty near of Kin. Only I find this vaſt difference between him and them: What he did innocently only for a Tryal of Skill, to ſhew his Wit and Oratory, and what an ingenious Man might be able to ſay on an ill Subject; theſe Men do in good earneſt, that is, ſtrain all their Faculties to the utmoſt in a real oppoſition of Juſtice. Nay, thoſe who not long ſince ſtrain'd all their Wit and Parts, and the Law it ſelf, to take away Mens Lives under pretence of Juſtice, contrary to Law, now ſtrain all to exempt the moſt notorious Criminals, deſerving the greateſt Severity from condign Puniſhment, by an <hi>Indefinite Act of Oblivion,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Indempnity,</hi> wherein I muſt confeſs they act very uniformly, before in ſuppreſſing, and now in oppoſing of Law and Juſtice, and always for their own Intereſt.</p>
            <p>So it muſt be; or, if we ſuppoſe them to believe that there is any ſuch thing as Juſtice at all, it muſt be granted that they have different Sentiments concerning the Crimes than we imagine, or however, than we have. And this is plainly the Truth. The one, in effect, will admit no Crime in King <hi>James</hi> precedent to his Departure. And the other will admit none in his Miniſters, Officers or Inſtruments. That, which we take to be <hi>Juſtice</hi> in that caſe, he calls <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> and <hi>Revenge,</hi> and thoſe who are for it, <hi>Blood-hounds, Bellowers for Vengeance, Hot-headed Animals,</hi> &amp;c. What we take to be great and notorious <hi>Crimes,</hi> he reputes <hi>Points Juſtifiable, or at leaſt doubtful, wherein the Juſtice of inflicting Puniſhments can never be vindicated;</hi> and begs <hi>the Readers Pardon for the Impropriety</hi> of calling them <hi>Puniſhments,</hi> though he <hi>will not name their proper Term.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Actions done in the laſt or former Reigns, about which the World hath been ſo much divided, if Lawful or not.</hi> And if this be not ſufficient to declare his Sentiments, concerning his propoſed Indefinite Act of Oblivion and univerſal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51025:19"/>he tells us plainly, <hi>Laſtly, Its conſiſtent with, and promotive of the Trueſt and Higheſt Juſtice,</hi> (that is, for King <hi>James</hi>) <hi>For in moſt of the Caſes</hi> (the thirteen Heads he had mentioned before, <hi>viz.</hi> The Heads Voted 23 <hi>Jan.</hi> to be Crimes for which ſome Perſons may juſtly be excepted out of the Bill of Indemnity) <hi>the Law is doubtful. And to puniſh Opinion in matters of Law, is as unjuſt as to proſecute Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes in matters of Religion is unchriſtian.</hi> So that here we have a Vindication, not indeed <hi>of the laſt Years Tranſactions,</hi> but what is more, of the Tranſactions of the laſt or former Reigns. And if this be good, my Opinion, which according to this Lawyers Judgment is not puniſhable, being in matter of Law, is, That King <hi>William</hi> hath no good Title, but he's a meer Uſurper, and we have catch'd at an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt an Innocent Man upon a timerous Flight or Departure, to keep him from his Right. My Opinion in this matter I have publiſh'd in Print more than once, and therefore will not repeat it here. But this is ſo evident a Conſequence of what he ſaith, that it is his Opinion, that I know not with what Colour or Pretence he could deny it if he would. Other Conſequences of his Diſcourſe I take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, becauſe not pertinent to my preſent purpoſe. But I think I may reaſonably recommend it to the conſideration of the Diſſenters, as that which may in ſome things afford as proper Topicks for them, as for any ſort of People of this Nation, that I know; and may be alledged with much more reaſon for them, than for his Party of Criminals. <hi>Veritas praevalebit one time or other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid I ſuppoſe it is very evident, that the Authors of <hi>The laſt Years Tranſactions Vindicated,</hi> and of the three Parts of <hi>The Magiſtracy and Government of</hi> England <hi>Vindicated,</hi> are near of Kin, at leaſt in their Principles, and Sentiments of the preſent Government under King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and of their Right and Title thereunto, and in the General Scope of theſe Writings, as near as in their Titles. And therefore this laſt coming ſo opportunely
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51025:19"/>to my hand, it doth not only confirm my Opinion of the former, but gives me a fair occaſion to conſider the matter of both, ſo far as concerns my Subject, with one and the ſame Labour. And therefore before I proceed to ſpeak of the Puniſhment of the Criminals in our Caſe, this Gentleman being a Lawyer, gives me occaſion to conſider of the Law by which they may be puniſhed: For if there be no Law for it, he is in the right, That they are not properly Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but <hi>Violence, where the Juſtice of the thing is not clear and undoubted.</hi> And ſo much by the way. I hope he will give me leave to ſay of the Executions of <hi>Stephen Colledge,</hi> my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> Colonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> &amp;c. that they were <hi>Violences,</hi> that is, in plain Engliſh, moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate, wilful and wicked Murders, being committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Colour and Pretence of Law; of moſt of which Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath been reverſed by Authority of Parliament; and that I think it differs not much in the fight of God, whether a Man have his Hand or his Tongue dip'd therein. And I doubt not but the great and good Sir <hi>Matthew Hale</hi> would have been of the ſame Opinion; which this Gentleman, who gives him thoſe deſerved Characters, will find ſome Reaſon to believe, if he pleaſe to peruſe but <hi>The Account of the Good Steward, concerning the Gift of Elocution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to the buſineſs. The Votes of 23 <hi>Jan.</hi> have enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated thirteen Heads of Crimes, for every one of which ſome Perſons may be excepted out of the Bill of Indemnity. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Puniſhments of theſe our Lawyer takes Exception, as <hi>Puniſhments never declared or promulged,</hi> and <hi>which by the Standing Laws and Common Juſtice of the Realm could not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</hi> That is to ſay, They are neither Treaſon, Felony, nor Miſdemeanours: For, for all thoſe there are Puniſhments declared, and to be inflicted by the Standing Laws and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice of the Realm. I muſt add, Nor Crimes puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by any Statute. And this is the leaſt that theſe Words can imply. So that we muſt ſuppoſe that they are nothing like any of thoſe we meet with in the Impeachments, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51025:20"/>Articles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt thoſe Flatterers, and Evil Counſellors and Inſtruments of Princes, which my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> mentions in his Chapter of Flattery, or any others to be found in our Records, Books of Entries, Reports, or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, not ſo much as thoſe concerning the High-Commiſſion Court, 17 <hi>Car.</hi> I. But the contrary of all this is ſo well known to all who have looked into the Records and Books afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that it is as needleſs as improper for this Paper to offer to recite them. But in ſtead of that, I will ſhew him that which is more, that is, That the Parliament may declare thoſe things to be Treaſon, (the puniſhment whereof is ſufficiently known) which never were, nor can now by the Ordinary Judges (though in the late Reigns they are believ'd to have exceeded their Bounds) be judged ſuch; and that by the expreſs Words of the Statute 25 E. 3. <hi rend="blackletterType">And becauſe that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> other <hi rend="blackletterType">like</hi> Caſes of Treaſon <hi rend="blackletterType">may happen in time to come, which a man cannot think or declare at this preſent time, it is accorded, That if any</hi> other Caſe <hi rend="blackletterType">ſuppoſed Treaſon, which is</hi> not above ſpecified, <hi rend="blackletterType">doth happen before any Juſtices,</hi> the Juſtices ſhall tarry <hi rend="blackletterType">without any going to Judgment of the Treaſon,</hi> till the Cauſe be ſhewed, <hi rend="blackletterType">and declared</hi> before the King and his Parliament, <hi rend="blackletterType">whether it ought to be adjudged Treaſon or other Felony.</hi> Beſides, for ſuch Crimes as are of their own Nature great Crimes, and not meerly by ſome poſitive Law of the State, there is neither Law nor Reaſon why the Legiſlative Authority in any State ſhould not order and inflict ſuch Puniſhments as they deſerve. And among thoſe may doubtleſs be reckoned all ſuch as have a direct tendency to the Subverſion of the Laws and Government of any State<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But Treaſon againſt the Kingdom, as well as againſt the King, may be found in our Books of Law and Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>And now I know not what moſt to admire in this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, his profound Skill in the Law, the Modeſty of his Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or his Honeſty and Conſcience. I cannot but think him a very proper Perſon to have been one of the <hi>Servants of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Crowns,</hi> one of the laſt Kings <hi>Miniſters, Officers or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51025:20"/>of Juſtice:</hi> He was certainly well qualify'd for lit, and his Zeal for their Vindication diſcovers that he had ſome concern of his own in it. And ſo confident a Gentleman, and ſo qualify'd, one would think ſhould get in ſomewhere now; at leaſt into the Parliament, and no doubt but ſet up by the Faction, and a great ſtickler there; one of thoſe, who are recommended by our Vindicators not only for Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Indemnity, but for Favour and Employment to our preſent King. And no doubt but he will be well ſerved by them, as well as he was the laſt Year.</p>
            <p>I cannot let this paſs without ſome further <hi>Reflection.</hi> It is not at all beſides the Deſign of my Writing, and no great Digreſſion from that particular matter I am now upon. Our other Vindicator tells us, that <hi>His Majeſty came a Stranger to</hi> England, <hi>and but darkly informed of the true.</hi> Arcana <hi>of the laſt two Reigns, and of the</hi> Practices <hi>and</hi> Principles <hi>of particular Men; it being ſo much</hi> their intereſt <hi>to vail them from his View: Whence it is to be ſuppos'd, that at his coming to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the Repreſentation made him of</hi> Perſons <hi>and</hi> Things, <hi>could not but receive a</hi> Tincture <hi>of the many different</hi> Principles <hi>and</hi> Intereſts <hi>of thoſe who made them. Conſidering which, it's no wonder that in ſuch a</hi> Maze of Buſineſs <hi>and</hi> Miſt <hi>of various Repreſentations, his Majeſty's Bounty might happen to to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plac'd in ſome one or other,</hi> page 29. I know not any thing more truly and reaſonably ſaid by that Writer. It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a great Diſadvantage his Majeſty was under, being unacquainted with the Principles and Intereſts of Perſons. And as that was juſt Cauſe both of Caution in the Choice, and of Excuſe of him from any ill Choice upon the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of others; ſo doth it aggravate the Fault of ſuch recommendations, and recommend the Service of ſuch as detect them. I ſhall therefore, for the more comple at De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of ſome ill Men, to what I have before obſerved, add this for Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Perſons</hi> concerned in theſe Vindications are Men of <hi>dangerour Principles in reſpect of the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51025:21"/>For if theſe Crimes be not puniſhable by Law, then are all they, who invited the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to come in with an Army, and all that aſſociated with him, Traytors; and he himſelf an Invader and Uſurper.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are Men of <hi>Arbitrary Principles,</hi> and ſo dangerous to the Nation, and the true ancient Conſtitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For if theſe Crimes be not puniſhable by Law, our Engliſh Monarchy is gone, and we are already fallen into a French or Turkiſh Tyranny.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are <hi>dangerous</hi> Perſons to be employed or truſted <hi>in reſpect of their Genius,</hi> Men of ſmooth voluble Tongues, and of Confidence to impoſe any thing. Of which I could add divers Inſtances to thoſe I have noted before: But I will add only this, becauſe it may ſerve alſo for another pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: He tells us, <hi>If the thirteen Heads,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>had been reduced into a Law—one third at leaſt of the Nation had been involved, who with their diſoblig'd Relations and Dependents, is not ſo contemptible a Flock,</hi> &amp;c. Now if every one of this third part had but one Relative or Dependent, they would make two thirds; if two, they would make the compleat num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Nation; but if many of them have 10, 20, 100, as many certainly have, they would far exceed the number of the People of this Nation. This I the rather mention, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I doubt not but they do greatly <hi>impoſe</hi> upon ſome Perſons, <hi>with this Pretence of their Number,</hi> which is falſe; and would be much leſs than it is, if they had not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where met with more Encouragement, than they expected.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are of <hi>the very ſame kind and Genius with thoſe Forty-One Mea</hi> I mentioned before, who by their Flatteries to raiſe themſelves, impoſed upon King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and ſo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned that Bloody War: And again in the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. to cover the Illegal Actions of themſelves or their Friends, impoſed upon the whole Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being then in a Tranſport, thoſe Declarations and Clauſes in ſome Acts, which are the occaſions of the Miſtakes and Diſſatisfaction of divers honeſt well-meaning Men now, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51025:21"/>of ſuch Diſſention an very much diſcompoſe and interrupt our compleat Settlement.</p>
            <p>Theſe being ſo dangerous Perſons both to the King and Kingdom, and having many (though not ſo many as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) of their Party and Principles, it cannot but be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that not only the King he cautious not to employ or entruſt them in any great matters, but that ſome good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion be made alſo by Parliament to ſecure both againſt them. And what leſs can that be, than an <hi>Act of Recognition,</hi> that the preſent King and Queen are rightful and lawful King and Queen, and to diſable all Perſons from ſitting in Parliament, or to hold any Place or Office of Authority or Truſt, who do not believe the ſame, and upon Oath declare ſuch their Relief and Recognitions accordingly?</p>
            <p>And now for <hi>Buniſhments.</hi> In all Puniſhments two things are to be conſidered: The Proportion in reſpect of the Crime, and the Conſequence. And as to the <hi>Crimes,</hi> it may be fit to be conſidered in our Caſe, Whether beſides the Thirteen Heads of Crimes <hi>committed in the laſt Reigns,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Votes, there have not been ſome of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture already committed <hi>in this,</hi> for which ſome Perſons may juſtly be excepted out of ſuch Bill of Indemnity? <hi>viz.</hi> Such as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The publiſhing of ſuch Libels, as by denying the Juſtice (of puniſhing the) Crimes aforeſaid, de manifeſtly undermine the very Grounds of our preſent Settlement, and the true Conſtitution of the Engliſh Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The adviſing the preſent King to ſuch things, as being done by the former Kings contrary to Law, ſeems to juſtifie their Illegal Actions, prejudice his own Cauſe, and tend to the diſturbance of the Government again. And it may be ſome others.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> Proportion and good Conſequence are always to be regarded. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> is <hi>leſs</hi> in Proportion than the Crime, and the <hi>Conſequence of Neceſſity or great Importance</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51025:22"/>for a future Security, of other publick Good, it is not Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but Injuſtice and Imprudence to forbear it, and a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er kindneſs to Criminals than to the Innocent.</p>
            <p>Such is the Excluding and diſabling ſuch Perſons from Truſts and Employments, is by former Violations and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors have ſhewed themſelves unfit to be further truſted.</p>
            <p>This hath indeed ſomething Penal in it, but ſo little, that it is nor properly a Puniſhment, but a neceſſary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Proviſion. This is the Caſe of the late King (of which more in the Apology for Mr. St.) and of his Counſellors and Agents. They who betray'd their Country and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too by Evil Counſel or Compliance, ought not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be admitted to Employments and Offices of Truſt, or to ſit in Parliament. Neither ought they to be returned, for they are not in truth <hi>beni &amp; legates homines.</hi> I ſpeak not of all his Counſellors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without diſtinction, as the mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Writer falſly ſuggeſts; but Evil Counſellors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who betrayed him as well as their Country.</p>
            <p>It will be a Blot and Mark of Ignominy upon this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to all Poſterity, to ſuffer thoſe perſons to ſit as judges, where thoſe Crimes are to be conſidered, whereof they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are notoriouſly guilty. And upon this occaſion I muſt ſay farther, That it is a Diſhonourable and an unreaſonable thing, to ſuffer perſons who have: raſhly (to ſay no more) foul'd their Hands in Innocent Blood, to fit in that Aſſembly; to ſuffer their Counſels, which ſhould be Sacred, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned by ſuch Company. Diſhonourable and unreaſonable are too ſoft Words for that; but I may very well uſe them concerning the permitting of Minors, who are diſable diary Law to diſpoſe of their own Eſtates, to ſit there. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Dignity of Parliaments ought to be preſerved? And therefore alſo, they who did preſume to Elect the ſame perſon to ſerve in this, who was expelled the Houſe the laſt Parliament, for their Affront to the Houſe ought to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51025:22"/>at leaſt by turning out Their Member again, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them no new Writ. For they deſerve not to have a Repreſentative in ſuch an Aſſembly, which they would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo factiouſly to affront; nor he to have a place there, who had ſo little regard to the Honour of it, and ſo little conſideration of what did become thoſe who choſe him. I write not this out of any Ill Will to any perſon, but out of great Good Will for the Honour and Service of my King and Country. In ſuch as are obnoxious, certainly Modeſty, to abſtain and retire for ſome time, would be the greateſt Prudence. But ſuch as will impudently threſt themſelves in, ought deſervedly to be thruſt out. The Honour of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ought not to be proſtituted for the ſake of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, be their Quality what it will. Nor are they Men of Vertue or Worth, who would ſerve themſelves at that rate. The Kingdom wants not Men of unſpotted and untainted Honeſty and Fidelity to be employed: But uſually the worſt are moſt forward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When the Puniſhment bears a juſt proportion to the Crimes, it ought generally ſpeaking, to be inflicted for the Maintenance of Juſtice, and Reſtraint of Evil. But there may be ſpecial Reaſons in reſpect of the Conſequence, either to inflict the Puniſhment, or pardon the Offenders.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Thirteen Heads of Crimes, there are two at leaſt, which I take to be <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and ought to be adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo by Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> The firſt concerning the Diſpenſing Power, and the third concerning the Commiſſion for Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Cauſes. I know there is another Puniſhment of, this laſt by the Statute of 17 <hi>Car.</hi> I. <hi>ch.</hi> 11. But in this Caſe the manifeſt Intention and Deſign of the King and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators by thoſe means to ſubvert the Government and the Laws, make them both Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe Crimes are of ſo high a Nature, and the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf having already ſuffer'd for the ſame Cauſe, both Juſtice and Prudence require, that all the Criminals, by whoſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs and Compliance the King was encouraged to thoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51025:23"/>Evil Courſes, be brought to Tryal, and have Sentence. Not only Juſtice, but Prudence doth require this, to aſſort a juſt and honeſt Cauſe, and to terrifie ſuch as ſhould dare to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in ſuch baſe and wicked Courſes hereafter. But above all, the Judges and Biſhops, who betray'd alſo their own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, ought to be made Examples. What ſpecial Reaſons there may be to mitigate any part of the Puniſhment in any of them, they being not many, belongs to the Parliament to conſider: But in general, they ought to be good and weighty.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, when the <hi>Offenders</hi> are many, and the <hi>Grime and Puniſhment Capital,</hi> it is uſual and reaſonable to puniſh only the Principals and moſt notorious, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all the reſt, as in caſes of Rebellion and Inſurrections; becauſe of the Evil Conſequence of taking away the Lives of ſo many Perſons, whereof perhaps many were miſſed by the Principal of them, and might prove good Men after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. In ſuch caſes they are all to be looked upon as one Body, and the taking off the Heads and Principals of them, is a kind of a capital Puniſhment of that Body of Men.</p>
            <p>But when the Crime and Puniſhment are of a lower Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as <hi>Miſdemeanors,</hi> (which being very various, the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is more diſcretionary, as Fine, or Fine and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both, according to the nature of the Crime) it is not ſo, nor is there any reaſon it ſhould: For a Pecuniary Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be inflicted on many without any Inconvenience. And in the preſent Caſes it may be proportioned according to the Rates aſſeſſed upon the Criminals in ſome of the late Taxes; and ſome Diſabilities might very properly be made part of the Puniſhment. But in theſe diſcretionary Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, divers things are to be taken into conſideration. And one or two I will mention on the ſide of Mercy: 1. The Example of our Heavenly father now, in our own eaſe, who hath ſhewed Mercy, and ſent ſo great a Deliverance, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſinful and wicked ſtate of the Nation. 2. The Papiſts and the wicked Examples of thoſe late Popiſh
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51025:23"/>Kings, have been the principal Corrupters of the Manners of the Nations; and therefore if they who have been miſlead by them, ſuffer not ſo deep, as otherwiſe they ought, it is but reaſonable.</p>
            <p>So much for <hi>Puniſhment of Criminals,</hi> and now for <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.</hi> The Vindicators think it <hi>an Invaſion upon the Kings own Liberty, to deny him the uſe of ſuch Perſons, as through the Temptations and Snares of a Court</hi> were guilty of Compliance <hi>in things blamable,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if their great Parts and Acquaintance with Affairs of State make them neceſſary:</hi> I have known ſome perſons cry'd up for notable, cunning and ſhrew'd Men, whom when I have hapned to underſtand more neerly, I have found to be Men of Craft indeed, but ſuch as did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; not ſo much in greater Knowledge of Buſineſs than other Men had, as in the uſe of a greater Latitude in Acting than ſome other Men would uſe. And ſuch Perſons may be ſo far from being neceſſary to a Prince, that they may be dangerous. As I remember one of thoſe cunning Men I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, being apply'd to by three Perſons then of good Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, for his Advice in a Cauſe, eaſie to have been relieved in Chancery, as it was afterwards, by his Cunning involv'd them all, and ſome others for Witneſſes, in a notorious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, Subornation and Perjury. Parts without Fidelity, which is inconſiſtent with Compliance in Blamable things, ought not to recommend any Man to a Prince's Service. This I ſay to ſhew the Inſufficiency of his Argument in that part. Nor am I ſo rigorous, as not to agree with him in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as he ſtates the Caſe; only the perſon ought to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary, and the Prince to be very cautious how far he relies upon him. Nay, I will go further with him, and ſuppoſe the Perſon ſtand accuſed, or even impeach'd in Parliament, I would not deny him the uſe of ſuch a perſon, in due time, that is, when he hath been try'd, and either cleared and acquitted, or for ſome ſpecial good cauſe legally pardon'd. Otherwiſe that, which thoſe perſons ſay is an <hi>Invaſion</hi> upon the Kings Liberty, to deny him, is an affront
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51025:24"/>to the <hi>Government,</hi> tends to the Subverſion of the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and to the diſparagement of the preſent Cauſe both of the King and Kingdom, makes it look like a matter of Trick and Violence, and not as I take it to be, of clear and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Juſtice. The Protection and Employment of Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals being one of the great Grievances of former Reigns, and as pernicious to the Kings as to the People. And if this be the Caſe of any perſon now employed, he cannot be a a good Man, or worthy of any Favour at all, if he would, deſire his own Security at the rate of ſo great an Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience both to the King, and to the Government, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally under our preſent Circumſtances; and not rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly retire for ſome time, and if innocent, modeſtly put himſelf upon a fair Tryal; or if Guilty of any thing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, humbly ſubmit and beg Pardon. And this is the trueſt Wiſdom in ſuch caſe: For they who obſtinately ſtand out in ſuch caſes, do uſually bring miſchief to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or the King; and the more highly they carry it out among Men, the more they provoke the Judgments of God upon themſelves, of Exciſion, or in ſome remarkable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, according to the Nature of the Crime. All Courts and Judicatures ought to maintain their Authority, and ſo much the more, when notoriouſly violated, or when there are any attempts to evade or oppoſe it. And eſpecially at this time when we are either doing Juſtice and Equity againſt the late King himſelf, or plainly playing Tricks with him, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Iniquity of our own Hearts.</p>
            <p>There is but one thing more, which I think worth my taking notice of in this Pamphlet, (for Trifles I have paſſed over good ſtore all along) and that is what he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 32. that <hi>The <hi rend="blackletterType">Calling,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Diſſolving of Parliaments</hi> is ordinarily one of the moſt myſterious Problems of State, and one of the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Touchſtones of Skill in the Art of Government.</hi> To Men of ill Deſigns, or who underſtand not the true Conſtitution of this Government, it may be ſo indeed: But to honeſt and underſtanding Men nothing is more eaſie. It was the Law
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51025:24"/>of this Nation before <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or any Statute now in Force was made, and it is ſtill the Law, That Parliaments be held once a year, or oftner if need be. And I will tell this Gentleman in the Words of King <hi>James</hi> I. that which will effectually explain this Myſtery, and ſolve the Problem. <hi>A King</hi> (ſays he) <hi>governing in a ſetled Kingdom, leaves to be a King, and degenerates into a</hi> Tyrant, <hi>as ſoon as he leaves off to rule according to his Laws.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Therefore all Kings, that are not</hi> Tyrants, <hi>or</hi> Perjured, <hi>will be glad to bound themſelves within the Limits of their Laws: And they who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them the contrary, are</hi> Vipers <hi>and</hi> Peſts, <hi>both againſt them and the Commonwealth.</hi> Speech 21. <hi>March,</hi> 1609. This moſt ancient Inſtitution, is not more ancient than wiſe, uſeful and neceſſary, and of a juſt proportion to the other parts of the Conſtitution. The Commons in the Counties are repreſented by the Grand Jury, who are to enquire and preſent what is amiſs there; and the Lords, by the Free-holders, who are the Judges. And as the Counties have their Court once in a Month, the Kingdom their Courts of Common Law for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and ordinary matters, four times in the year, that is in effect, once in a Quarter, ſo the whole State had, and ſtill ought to have their Seſſion for Publick and Extraordinary matters concerning the whole Kingdom, once in the year. The great buſineſs of this is to enquire into, and inſpect the Actions of the Great Officers, Privy Counſellors and Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and of the King himſelf, if he do any thing contrary to Law, and the common Intereſt of the Nation; to interpret their own Laws, where there is occaſion, and reſolve other Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; to receive and hear Petitions, redreſs Grievances, and give Relief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this is an Inſtitution as much for the Honour, Safety and Eaſe of the Prince, as for the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Commodity of the People. For if the Prince act as he ought to do, by Advice of Privy Council, and of ſuch perſons as in their ſeveral Places are by Law to adviſe him: The Parliament, being to convene within the year, muſt needs be ſuch a Check to them, that they will rarely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51025:25"/>dare to propoſe any thing miſchievous or illegal; and more rarely be able to bring it to effect; and whatever it be, the King is ſecure, and the Counſellor or Officer to anſwer for it. Now an Inſtitution of ſo great Antiquity, ſo agreeable to the other parts of our Conſtitution, of ſo great Importance in the Government, ſecured by two ſeveral Acts of Parliament in the Reign of that wiſe and magnanimous Prince <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. ſtill in force, beſides others, ought not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to be eluded with vain Pretences of Reaſon of State, and abuſed, as it hath been, by the whole laſt Race of our Kings, to their own hurt, and to the great diſturbance, and almoſt Diſſolution of a moſt Noble Conſtitution, to gratifie ill Men, by long Intermiſſions, abrupt Prorogations and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and by long Continuances for no other reaſon but to corrupt the Members to betray their Truſt. As by Law they ought to be aſſembled once a year, ſo ought they alſo by Law to fit effectually till all Grievances be redreſſed, and buſineſs diſpatch'd before their Departure, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. p.</hi> 11. For if our <hi>Kings</hi> by their <hi>Oath,</hi> be obliged to Govern according to Law, they are certainly obliged to it in this particular, it being the chief part of the Government. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentum departiri non debet dummode aliqua Petitio pendeat indiſcuſſa, vel ad minus ad quam non fit determinatum Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum. Et <hi rend="blackletterType">ſi Rex contrarium permittat perjurus eſt,</hi>
               </hi> ſaith the Ancient <hi>Modus tenendi Parliament.</hi> of which Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows ſome Copies he had ſeen to be as ancient as <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. Tit. of <hi>Hon. p.</hi> 611. But this is not a place to inſiſt more largely upon this matter; nor indeed doth it need it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
